So, someone asked says, "Ajun, it's
often said that you claim you must wait
until you're a stream enterer in order
to meditate."
>> Mhm.
>> How do Well, I guess is that true?
>> What What um or is that a
misrepresentation? And the second question is if it is
And the second question is if it is
true, how do you suggest one waits until
then without getting bored?
Well, it depends.
>> Do we say you you have to wait the
stream in order to meditate?
>> What do you mean by meditation?
>> If you mean concentration, concentration
on your nostrils,
>> watching objects,
>> calming techniques,
>> then that comes neither before nor after
stream entry.
>> Mhm.
>> There's no place for that in the actual
practice. So what meditation do we refer
to then when we say you got to be a
sautana to meditate rightly?
>> Well, it's the things that the sas
actually describe like the four batanas
the jannaas the
reflections on a sububa meta
things that would purify your mind.
>> So why but why would I why can't I just
start doing that now? Why do I need to
wait for sodapati?
>> Well, it's not that you need to wait.
It's that you need to keep in mind that
what you're doing now will be
inaccurate. >> Why?
>> Why?
>> Because you don't see your mind clearly.
>> Uhhuh.
>> Which is the criteria.
>> Seeing the mind clearly.
>> Yeah. So when you see your mind clearly,
why is that important? Well, because
these contemplations are not for the
sake of doing them. They're for the sake
of purifying the mind from greed,
aversion, and delusion. So if if you
don't see greater aversion and delusion
because you don't see your mind
>> then you don't even have the target. You
don't even see the target where you
would be aiming these shots.
>> Why wouldn't you why wouldn't someone be
seeing the mind? What would be
preventing them in seeing the mind?
>> Well, lack of the gradual training grad
lack of development in gradual training
and views that they haven't clarified
sufficiently or abandoned wrong views.
But obviously you know you don't know
what you don't know. So how can you
abandon the wrong views when you don't
know they're wrong?
>> Well yeah you don't abandon them as
>> so how do you abandon them?
>> It's through the training in the
precepts and sensory trait.
>> Right. So through training
in certain actions
that well curb and then eventually not
give in at all to greed aversion
delusion. That's how you uncover the
mind. Yeah.
>> Whether you think about seeing the mind
or not, it's irrelevant in a way really.
>> Yeah. The like you have those wrong
views as a symptom of the fact that you
haven't [clears throat] been
>> training in these things efficiently.
>> Yeah. Yeah. That's that's what the sa
says through purification of behavior.
You purify the views.
>> Through purification of behavior that
purifies the views, you purify the mind.
M so whether one is thinking and
unraveling their views or not if they're
not celibate withdrawn from sensuality
or at least
not lying to themselves about that
that's the direction of training that
they need to develop and built towards
they're not going to be seeing their
mind doesn't matter how much they
theorize about it.
>> Yeah. So clarifying the wrong views to
be clear doesn't mean that kind of yeah
uh reflecting on it is a dry kind of
subject. It's happens through for
example um when you start keeping the precepts
um when you start keeping the precepts
when you start um restraining your
actions that you were not restraining
before uh whether you like it or not these um
uh whether you like it or not these um
wrong emphases will start coming up like
you might start having the natural
response to try to deny things to try to
deal with the objects withdraw even more
than >> you're already withdrawn celibacy and so
>> you're already withdrawn celibacy and so
on And you would have to overdo it.
>> Yeah. You would have to then come face
to face with your actual views whether
you like it or not. Your views of where
the problem is.
>> So you would be dealing with them
>> and abandoning those views not by
theorizing but by meeting the challenges
that will arise
>> through the sense restraint through the
virtue. >> So um so back onto the the original
>> So um so back onto the the original
question. So say
um there's no place for any
cal concentration self hypnotic practice
in terms of the actual dharma and
training. Um, you could say that all of those
meditation kind of meditations or or
views about it or practices, they do
kind of say are rooted in a certain
degree of need like a in a type of need
like you need to do something palpable
about the practice.
>> So meditation often serves that purpose.
you know yes I keep I can keep the
precepts I can do this but what do we do
like um directly in terms of the and
that's how people like fall into this
palpable sensation tactile watching and
so on and convince themselves through
their views as we discussed in our talks
so say somebody's not doing that but
that palpable need is still there
>> and so they they're not sautana they
don't see the mind they are training in
precepts and they need to do something
more acutely
about the practice is still there. Is
there something that they could do to
fulfill that need?
>> Well, why?
>> Well, I just too too pressuring, too
strong. Like if I don't do something
that will kind of maintain some sort of
secondary identity of me is the one who
practices, I will just completely drift
away and stop even keeping the precepts.
I need some something grounding to to
kind of keep me in touch with my idea of
what the dharma practice is because at
this stage that's the only thing I have.
I don't see the mind. I don't see the
dharma. I have the idea of the practice
that can be maintained and fueled
through the need of doing something
about it. Is there something I can be
doing about it?
>> Well, why not see that as a problem?
Because too subtle to see that. That
pressure, that compulsion is just too
subtle to see. like I yeah it's a
problem they said it's a problem but I
doesn't have gravitas that thought
>> well
>> so are there other things I can actually
when I feel a need to sit down and
practice in a quiet secluded environment
in a quiet secluded environment
is this something that hillside
uh recommends or allows that I can do
>> well ask yourself first of all make a
practice out of reflecting in What ways
are you still giving into greed urgent
and delusion knowingly?
>> Say that again. Make a practice
>> out of reflecting.
>> Uhhuh.
>> In what ways are you still giving in to
give some practical examples? So say um
evening my day is finished. Came back
from work
family doesn't matter. I'm sit sit quiet
in the room. What do I think about?
How do I go about that reflection?
>> Did is there any practical way? Did in
the course of my day my mind pressured
pressure me out of some obsessive kind
of compulsion with something?
>> Yes number of times you discovered it
>> and I gave into it.
>> What next?
>> Well, contemplate the danger of doing
that. >> Contemplate how the fact that
>> Contemplate how the fact that
>> I don't see the danger of doing it. If I
did, I wouldn't have done it.
>> Well, yeah. Exactly. So you have to you
have to realize if you're claiming to be
practicing towards this goal of freedom
from craving.
>> Well, I am just obviously I'm failing.
>> Yeah. So if that is your goal, then you
want to see well I shouldn't then be
giving into craving
and you're clearly doing that but you're
not aware of it because you're not
making an effort
>> to see those connections.
>> Uhhuh.
>> Between craving and the actual
day-to-day actions that you're doing. So
then do you mean that
say a person I sit and reflect and then
I see that number of times I gave into
craving. Um
Um
do you do you mean that reflecting on
that will gradually
will gradually
prevent me from giving into craving when
the pressure comes up?
>> Yeah. by building up the context that
>> so I can make a practice out of that
>> because the problem is these things are
not included
these acting out of pressures more
subtle pressures than the preset and so
on that's not included in your vision of
what needs to be avoided
>> because you have
>> when those things come up
>> so then practically speaking at the end
of the day I feel I have a need to sit
quietly so instead of
doing um body calming body scanning or
something saying I should think about my
actions throughout the day.
>> Yeah.
>> Fundamentally that's what you're saying.
>> And you would find
>> how many times I acted this or this
>> not for some sake of inventory or
something. >> Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> But just
>> bringing them up and leaving them in the
mind so the mind can also see that.
>> Yeah. and and highlighting like
this is where the training applies
because then if you're not thinking
about it, you will just continue as you
said clearly you already don't see it.
>> So it's not like it's magically going to
be uncovered.
You're just going to continue in the
same direction not seeing that as a
problem and emphasizing your efforts
toward practice towards these other
secondary things.
>> Well, they kind of does go hand in hand
usually. It's like for people well for
whom the the main emphasis of the
practice is on the contemporary
meditation techniques
virtue sense restraint will always be
optional basically secondary or optional
like they would do it and many would not
be like dare to deny it publicly because
obviously suas are full of talking about
it
>> as a requirement but internally ally
it's it's always going to be a relegated
second place purpose.
>> Yeah.
>> Um
>> and it would be taken as like a easy
superficial thing that by being a monk
for example you already did.
>> Yeah.
>> But you wouldn't realize there's all
these layers to it. Things of still
actions by body by speech even that you
did >> that were coming out of greed aversion
>> that were coming out of greed aversion
and delusion and the practice would have
been not to do them. Mhm.
>> So then your uh emphasis of these other
things means like you're not even seeing
this otherwise you wouldn't be
>> would it be right to say the basis of
that that say even if somebody um
is trying to keep the precepts and they
are failing repeatedly. So on one level
they know they're not obscuring what the
direction of the practice is. But on
another level more often than not when
the pressures come up on a day-to-day
basis they have no strength but to give
into it. Mhm.
>> Would it be correct to say that that
also kind of could be boiled down to
they they're not frequently
recollecting even methodically recollecting setting a
even methodically recollecting setting a
time of a day aside to sit down and
recollect on the choices and actions
you've been making and doing yesterday
and day before and today and the ones
you're planning.
>> Yeah. If the pattern you start to see
the pattern automatically
you start getting the motivation to do
something about it.
>> So so you say somebody makes the effort
and you know as I said you know
sometimes they keep the precepts better
sometimes they fail they feel bad and so
on but that they make the effort to
think about
all the actions and choices they made
throughout the day and how many of those
were rooted in greed, aversion, obvious
compulsion. Is there
Is there
what's the next step in a way is like is
is there something that that
contemplation should now kind of lead to
like so I started doing that and what's
what now
>> do I just do it and leave it or do I go
further with it?
Well, if you
if you
if you're not confident like, okay,
these are
>> the things that I shouldn't have done.
>> Well,
>> so you you are you are you are like
that's clear. As I said, the direction
of what practice is is clear. So, you're
not like trying to justify
>> sensuality and so on and say it's not an
obstacle and what not. You know, but you
keep failing.
>> Yeah. So, well, now that you've
clarified those things, go about your
day knowing
where those traps are
because that's how you don't step on
them. >> Reminding yourself of the traps.
>> Reminding yourself of the traps.
>> Reminding yourself of the traps. Yeah.
>> So then there is really no um resolution
to that contemplation. It's more like
just realigning
>> the state of affairs.
>> Yeah. Because the problem is not that
you haven't discovered some magical
truth. The problem is you yourself keep
choosing to act out of creative version
and delusion.
>> So then you see this, you see the ways
that you're doing that and then your
next step is to not do it.
>> That's already implicit.
>> Yeah.
>> So it's more like forgetting
forgetting about not doing it is how you
do it. Yeah.
>> So frequently recollecting the purpose
of of I mustn't forget about this
>> and the fact that yeah if you like you
said even methodically you need to
remind yourself this is against the
training this is going to take me away
from what I'm trying to develop because
>> like broad the values.
>> Yeah. It's because it's like it might
seem like um I don't know redundant or
pointless to remind yourself of that but
the thing is when you went and did those
things you were not clear about them. I
think that's exactly probably the case.
It does become almost like self-evident.
Yeah, I already know this.
>> Yeah.
>> But see, if you if you had kept that
knowing there at that time, you wouldn't
have done it.
>> If it was strong enough,
>> if it was strong enough, it would if it
was made a basis, you wouldn't have
engaged in those actions to begin,
>> right? So, you know it on some level,
but it's not about knowing it.
>> Yeah.
>> It's about actively having it present in
your mind.
>> Yeah.
It's like
>> and you wouldn't have it present in your
mind because you would ignore it and not
frequently bring it up.
>> Yeah. It's like you know you are walking
in the minefield [snorts] but because
you're dealing with this and doing that
you eventually forget that there are
places that you shouldn't step on and
that's because you were just not
protecting the
>> you start overlooking the specific
places where you where you are stepping
on. >> Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Although it's still it's not not true to
say I know about it. somebody told you
you would say yes of course I know
>> but in that moment where you get
distracted with other things you're not
aware of it
>> right so then so you're not doing this
contemplation for some sort of uh new
knowledge or something it's more like
stuff that's
>> well there was kind of almost always
self-evident >> what's good what's bad in a sense
>> what's good what's bad in a sense
>> but by actually making a point
>> of sitting down and actively thinking
about
that is something that can be done then
>> even by somebody who doesn't see their
mind >> um who still acts out of the duty to do
>> um who still acts out of the duty to do
something out of the idea of practice
>> that that would be a right thing to do
like that wouldn't be as as misguided
>> yeah and then automatically if you did
that properly it would start become
becoming apparent how redundant all the
other practices would have been
>> anything because it wouldn't have ever
revealed these [snorts] things to you
and the fact that you'd have abstained
from them. You would just hoped that
that's going to be resolved on its own.
If I just double down in this.
>> So you would just like it's like doing
some kind of voodoo dance to stop the
fire >> while on the side you're just throwing
>> while on the side you're just throwing
fuel at it still.
>> Well, you're dancing, choosing to go and
stand in the fire and dance.
>> So you become the fuel. Yeah.
It's also how you wouldn't become
dependent even on that cuz uh because
that's how you hesitated at the
beginning to even say something because
whatever you would say would fill that
space that would be a barrier between
you and that and that mind pressuring
you to do something
>> which was the original
>> but then your emphasis will start to
shift. there are these things that I
shouldn't do
>> rather than like
>> I need to keep doing it.
>> Yeah. And eventually that would even
come to I need to contemplate what I've
been doing during the day.
>> And you become aware of that and
recognize that's already a
contemplation. >> Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. You could see how even that
misguided need that I you know described
as kind of almost part of that
>> identity of the one who practices that's
what keeps you in touch with the
practice. people started like it's it's
real as such that you can't
>> yeah it's wrong but you can't just stop
it
>> but if you were to
>> as we describe as the suta describe
reflect on your actions
>> like not just in passing not just once
and then okay I know it now but make a
point of whether I know it or not
whether it feels clear whether it feels
redundant I will still do it
>> I will still bring up questions self
questioning why did I do this how many
times when that compulsion arose how how
when that compulsion arose how how
strong was how weak was I
>> is there a chance for me to not do it
where I'm at in terms of being
overwhelmed by the mind and stuff could
have prevented some of those compulsions
did they result on account of my other
careless choices they were not
necessarily so compulsive and so on
thinking about that will actually more
and more
>> put even that need to do something
mechanically so to speak will align it
better and make it non- mechanic because
it's just going to align it with where
your intentions are and then you
recognize, oh, this is actually what the
practice is.
>> Yeah. And and pattern that you will
probably start recognizing pretty soon
is you kind of have these actions that
feel like if you would have really
questioned yourself, you would know it's
root in the wrong intention,
>> but you kind of downplay how bad it is.
You think, "Oh, well, yeah, sure.
>> I'll think about it later.
>> I'll think about it later. I'll deal
with it later right now. I need to do
this. This is top priority." And then
you would see it's because of that that
then all these other actions become even
harder to say no to.
>> Yeah. And when you think about things
later if then remorse comes up because you
if then remorse comes up because you
recognize I could I could have
restrained myself. I didn't.
>> You allow that remorse. Yeah.
>> That's
>> that's the payment for it basically.
>> That's how you will strengthen the value
for next time. Yeah. Not to do it.